[MUSIC]
Hi everyone, and welcome to Understanding
the Brain.
We're going to talk about the neurobiology
of everyday life.
I'm really excited about this.
I've learned so much by preparing for this
class
and I think that we're going to learn a
lot
as we, as you go along in this class and
as we talk to each other every week.
Just to give you an overview of what we're
going to concern ourselves
with, I want to share with you a story
which is, really shows the
power and the profundity of what our
nervous system does for us.
And the story is by Jean-Dominique Bauby
and
it's called The Diving Bell and the
Butterfly.
Jean-Dominique Bauby was the editor of
ELLE, the leading fashion magazine in
France.
And he lived in Paris and he lived a very
exciting cosmopolitan life.
He had two children.
And one day, he was driving and he had a
sudden onset
incapacitation.
It turned out to be a stroke, a massive
stroke in his brain stem.
He, he says in the beginning of the
prologue before
this happened, he'd never even heard of
the brain stem.
Well, you're going to hear about the brain
stem.
So he had this massive stroke in the brain
stem and this left him paralyzed.
So he couldn't move his arms or his legs.
He couldn't point.
He was on a respirator because he could
not breathe on his own.
He couldn't swallow.
So he was they had to deal with him
drooling.
At one point in, in this book, which I'll
tell
you how he wrote in a minute he says, he
was
very happy to get his own clothes back
because if he
had to drool he at least wanted to drool
on cashmere.
So so what, how did he write this book?
He's paralyzed.
He can't write.
He can't speak.
He's on a respirator.
He can't move his laryngeal muscles, he
can't
really form his upper airway to form
words.
So how did he do it?
Well, it turns out that people with this
syndrome, and
it's called the Locked-in syndrome, often
times can move an eyelid.
And indeed he could move an eyelid.
And they, they realized that because in
fact,
Locked-in syndrome patients often are able
to do that.
So, what they, what occurred was, there
was a, a French alphabet.
In other words, the most common letters in
the
French language were listed from most
common to least common.
And when a person would point to each one
of
these letters or read them aloud and when
they got
to the correct letter Bauby would blink
his working eyelid
and he blinked out letter by letter this
entire story.
That's, that's just such an amazing
action, such an amazing accomplishment.
So with the one avenue that Bauby had to
express himself he did, and he did so
extremely eloquently.
I just reread this, I think I've read it
five
or six times, and it's just a really
interesting, moving book.
And what struck me when I read it this
time was, was the craving, the
craving for, for expression, for life, for
participation.
He unfortunately
he died just after this book was
published, it,
it's, it's a hard thing to live, with the
body not, being supported by, by the
central nervous system.
So the title, The Diving Bell and the
Butterfly, refers to his, his yin and
yang.
He's in a diving bell, in the sense that
his body is not under his control.
He cannot move.
He is paralyzed.
At the same time, he has all sorts of
sensory abnormalities.
He's feeling, he feels pain, even though
he can't feel touch.
He can not feel actual stimuli, actual
things that are happening to his
body, but he feels these abnormal
sensations akin to amputation pain.
There's nothing there, but a person feels
pain.
Well, he feels that kind of sensation as
well.
So he's stuck in this diving bell.
A diving bell is an iron globe that you
can, that people
used to use to, as submersibles to go down
into the ocean.
And he, that's all he can do is be in
this in this constrained existence where
he can't actually move himself.
But at the same time, he can, he can soar.
He can soar with his brain.
He can soar in his thoughts and his
emotions, his memories and his feelings.
And he does and he describes for instance
one, he
describes his feelings about Empress
Eugenie at the Naval Hospital.
And he describes this entire interaction
with at the hall in the Naval Hospital
with these various pieces of art, and he
describes it all in the present tense.
It's as real as, as if it's happening.
It's happening in his brain and in fact,
that's our reality.
So, we're going to use The Diving Bell and
the Butterfly, and Bauby's experiences,
his, the things that
he lost, the things that he retained as a
framework within which we can explore the
nervous system.
Okay, we're going to get started now.
[MUSIC]