[MUSIC]
So in this segment we're going to map
these four basic functions
onto the brain, onto the central nervous
system, I should say.
So if we come over here, what we see is
what you would find if
you opened up the skull and you were
looking at the brain from the side.
So, this is the back, this is the front,
and this entire,
everything that you see here, all of this,
this is the forebrain.
It's all that you can see from the
outside, from the side.
Back here, this is part of the brain stem.
It's actually a part that's called the
cerebellum.
So, this is part of the brain stem and
then if
we follow this further back, we would get
to the spinal cord.
Now, the separation between the brain and
the spinal cord is
the, the brain is contra, is contained in
the skull,
and then there's an opening in the skull
called the
foramen magnum where the brain actually
attaches to the spinal cord.
And the spinal cord is contained in a
different set of bones called the
vertebral column.
Okay.
So now what we're going to do is we're
going to take a view from
the middle of the brain and we're going to
look at the medial surface.
We're going to, we're going to cut like
this
and look into the middle of the brain.
So here we have a brain and once again we
see this, this appearance that we saw from
the outside.
This is part of the forebrain.
In fact, the forebrain goes all the way
through here.
All of this is forebrain.
This back here is brain stem.
And
it's split into a hindbrain, which is all
of this and a mid brain.
We'll look at that more later.
But this entire bit, the mid brain and the
hind brain,
is the brain stem and back here is the
spinal cord.
So where do these four different
functions, where do they map onto?
Well, let's start with mo, with voluntary
movements.
Now voluntary movements means moving your
skeletal muscle, your voluntary muscles.
And there's only one neuron type that
leave the central nervous system
and goes directly to muscles, and that's
the, that's the motor neuron.
And there aren't very many of them.
There's under a hundred thousand, out of
200 billion neurons in the central nervous
system.
So, they're rare.
They're a very special type of neuron.
If they die, you can no longer move that
muscle.
Now, where are the motor neurons?
The motor neurons are contained either in
the brain stem or in the spinal cord.
But, there are no motor neurons in the
forebrain.
So the neur, motor neurons in the brain
stem move the face, move the mouth,
move the larynx, and are responsible for
speech and swallowing, facial expressions,
things like that.
The motor neurons in the spinal cord are
responsible for doing all this stuff.
All of our arms, our legs, our trunk, all
of our
movement that we do with our body happens
through the spinal cord.
Perception, remember that perception is
the
conscious perception of, of sensory
inputs,
the conscious appreciation of sensory
and that depends entirely on the
forebrain.
In fact, the appreciation of sensory
inputs, the conscious
appreciation of sensory inputs depends on
the cerebral cortex.
All of this, all of these hills and
valleys, this entire surface, is all
cerebral cortex.
This is what is required for perception.
If you don't make it up to cerebral
cortex, there is no perception that can
occur.
Okay?
So the information can come in through the
spinal cord, through the brain stem, even
through the
forebrain, but it has to make it to
this area, to this cerebral cortex, this
outer mantle.
Homeostasis is a very distributed process.
It depends on the forebrain, it depends on
the
brain stem, and it depends on the spinal
cord.
So up in forebrain, the contribution to
homeostasis is hormonal.
In brain stem, the, in the brain stem, the
contribution is, is varied.
It's, it's both through autonomic
changes, automatic changes that we're not
conscious of and we don't consciously
control, as well as consciously made
movements, and the
same is true for the, for the spinal cord.
And finally, higher abstract functions
depend entirely on the forebrain.
That's, that's all, they all take place.
It's like cog wheels just running around
in the forebrain.
So, even if you didn't have the brain stem
and the spinal cord, if
you could keep this forebrain alive, the
thoughts and emotions could, could turn
their wheels.
So, higher abstract functions are a, are a
outcome of,
of this, this same cerebral cortex that is
required for perception.
And in fact, perception is one of the
higher abstract functions
that we have, but we're also going to look
at it separately.
Okay, so what we have is different ca,
capacities in the different areas.
The forebrain is critical to higher
function,
language, memory, emotion, thought, all of
that.
Brain stem and spinal cord are a little
bit
of a mix and match where they're very good
doers.
They can, they can move and they are
pathways for ascending, for
incoming sensory input, as well as for
outgoing homeostatic adjustments.
In the next segment, what we're going to
look at is
how the nervous system partners with the
periphery to produce functions.
[MUSIC]