[MUSIC]
Okay, so we're going to talk about myelin
now.
Myelin is a, is a fatty wrap that goes
around some axons.
Now, what's the difference between a
myelinated axon and a naked axon?
A naked axon is one that doesn't have
mylelin, so it's unmylinated.
so, an unmylinated, or naked axon, can
only, transfer information at a slow rate.
So the rate that it's transfers
information is 0.2 to 1 meters per second.
That means to go 1 and a half
meters, which is roughly the distance
between [COUGH]
my toe, and right here.
To go that distance would take me seconds.
At least, a second and a half.
And probably more like 5 seconds.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, once we put on myelin, information
transfers much much faster.
It can go between 2 and 120 meters per
second.
If it goes at 120 meters per second, the
whole game is over.
Information is gone from here to here in
12 milliseconds.
.012 seconds.
So very short time, in perceptible to us.
And that is a, obviously a very useful
thing, so
that we can get information in time to
actually use it.
So, the information that we need the,
the fastest is information about keeping
our balance.
And so, as we walk along, if we bump
into something and we stumble, we need
that information fast.
If we had to wait for a second or two,
we'd be on the ground.
All the neurons that support our posture
against gravity, those neurons transfer
information really fast.
Alright, so let's talk a little bit
more about the information that gets
transferred.
That information occurs in, it's a 0 or a
1.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There's either an a point of information
or not.
And so it's very much like a computer
code, where what we're seeing is a series
of
of 0s or 1s and what's important,
the 0s are less important but the temporal
pattern of these ones is very important.
So, we want to know, at every millisecond,
is there a 1 or is there a 0?
If there's a 1 we want to know the
temporal pattern of those ones.
That's the neural code.
And these ones are actually, I, I'm
going to give you the name for that.
That's an action potential,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
also called a spike.
And we talk about firing spikes, neurons
fire spikes.
So, the timing of these spikes is what
carries information.
The spikes are going to travel down this
axon, so lets now imagine
in this situation that blue here is
supposed to be the miling.
These are wraps and their wraps that go
around the axon.
I, I've, I've drawn it as a cut away, but
the wrap will go all the way around here.
And the information, the spikes actually
jump.
That's what makes it so fast.
They don't have to they don't have to,
actually be
carried through the places with the
Myelin, they can actually jump.
And so things, anthra, the spike
information
is transferred very quickly, down this
axon.
Now, if we lose this myelin, if we lose
this myelin, just
a little bit of myelin here, now, this is
going to creep along.
And it actually, it's either going to be
really slowed or it may fail altogether.
So, this if our original message is this.
[SOUND].
And now, we have a demyelinating disease,
what
we're going to end up with is something
that's
spread out, because it's slower.
And every once in a while, it's going to
miss bits.
And now, the neuron that we're talking to
is getting a very incoherent message.
This is very different from this and that
is the problem with demyelination.
By, because an [UNKNOWN] because axons are
demyelinated, the information transfer is
very degraded.
It's a garbled message and that's a
problem.
And so in the next segment what we're
going to look at is the two different
major types of demyelinating diseases.
[MUSIC]