[MUSIC]
So, let's talk about what makes neurons
unique.
And here, I, I really apologize in
advance.
I'm going to show you pictures.
Of neurons that, that I filled and
stained.
And these neurons are actually, they're
sort of like members of my family.
For instance, this neuron right here, I
have incredibly deep, fond feelings for.
So, yeah I understand that not maybe
everyone feels that way but,
indulge me for a moment, we're going to
look at a few pictures.
so, here is a neuron and this piece right
here is the cell body,
these are the dendrites They you can see
that they divide, they divide a few times.
We not the whole, the whole thing's not in
focus,
we're going to see later a reconstruction
of this lovely cell.
Okay so that's the dendrites and then
here, this
is the axon and you can see that the, now
I'm going to take away these lines, you
can see
that the axon has a different appearance
from the dendrites.
The dendrites have their own appearance.
Now I'm going to show you another cell.
My feelings are not quite as deep for this
cell, but it's a nice cell.
So here's a cell and here is the cell
body.
These are dendrites, you can see and
they're dividing, like this.
Here's a dendrite, dendrites, etc.
And you can see that the, the appearance
of this
cell is very different from the appearance
of the last cell.
Now we're going to see a, a
reconstruction.
What I did was I actually drew out the
entire cell.
And we're going to look at a few
reconstructions and we're going to
see, once again, that there's great
variety in how these neurons look.
And all of these neurons, that I'm showing
you, are all in the same nucleus.
They're in the same location.
They got the same address, but they look
really different.
If you have the same address and you're in
the lung, you are not looking different.
So, this is really what's really, really
different about neurons.
Neurons are very unique.
Very, very unique is a little bit of a of
a toxism but they are, they are unique.
and, and unlike cells of other organs.
Ok, so here's a, a reconstruction.
And this line here, that's got the arrows
on it.
That's the axon.
The rest of this is the dendritic arbor.
And you can see that the dendritic arbor
gives you an area.
This is where the neuron is collecting
information from.
Okay?
So, the dendrites are taking information
in and this entire arbor,
describes a volume from which the neuron
will listen to information.
Here's a different looking cell.
This is, in fact, my, my deeply fond cell,
451.
Hm.
Okay, so here's the cell, and it's a
beautiful cell.
It's got this, it's got a very large,
dendritic arbor.
It's listening to a lot of cells.
And, and then it also has an axon which is
not shown on this, reconstruction.
And finally there's, here's a, a very
simple cell.
This is a cell, actually, that contains
the neurotransmitter serotonin.
And these other, the other calls did
not contain serotonin, they contained
other neurotransmitters.
And you can see in this reconstruction,
it's a pretty simple cell.
There are only two primary dendrites, and
they only divide a, a few times.
So the, there's not that huge arbor.
There's not that very delicate or
elaborated arbor.
I've spent my scientific life, staining
cells in one place, in one
nucleus and that nucleus tends to have, or
has, cells that are fairly simple.
In contrast, we know that there are other
cells that are very
complex, and this is one that I, I thank
Giorgio Grasselli for.
This is a purkinje cell in the cerebellum,
and you can
see that it has elaborate, it has a very
elaborate dendritic arbor.
Each one of these dendrites has actually
little, protuberances
called spines and that's what makes it
look really hairy.
The cells that I filled don't have spines
and here's
the axon for the cell, it's going to go
down like this.
So it's collecting information up here in
the
arbor and it's sending information down
like that.
In addition to variety in the size and the
shape of the soma,
the cell body, as well as the dendrites,
there's variety in the axon.
And so, I'm just going to show you these
pictures.
If they speak to you, fabulous.
If they don't, that, that's okay too.
So here's the, you can see the out of
focus, this is the axon, it's the parent
axon.
And it gives off branches or collaterals
and on these collaterals
are little, little swellings and these are
all synaptic terminals.
So that's what this, that's what the words
that
I have used, that's what it really looks
like.
Here is another, this is a different
appearance.
So here is the axon.
This is the axon and you can see that it
gives off these little, terminals
and it also has places where there's just
simply a swelling, on root.
So these are all synaptic, this a synaptic
terminal,
this is a synaptic terminal, this is an
axon.
So what we've just looked at is a wide
variety of ways in
which the anatomy of different neurons
can,
can make them different from each other.
And the anatomy is different in
appearance, but it's also
different in the sense of, what is a
neuron connected to?
What neurons are talking to it and what
neurons is it talking to?
So the inputs and the outputs of each
neuron are going to be different.
They're either going to be very, very
different or slightly different.
In addition to the anatomy, it's, the
other differences include the, what we
call excitability.
And this is essentially, how talkative is
the neuron?
How much do you have to goad it to get it
to say something?
And some neurons are, you know, they're
talking all the time.
And some neurons are very laconic, very
unlikely to speak.
And so, whether a neuron is, is, is very,
very likely or very unlikely to fire
action potentials, this is
a, another way in which different neurons,
are different from each other.
And finally there's, how do they speak?
And what we're talking about is the
neurotransmitter.
What is the neurotransmitter or what's the
chemical, the substance that the neuron
uses?
And we saw one neuron there that was using
serotonin.
But other neurons use other
neurotransmitters.
And we can think about this rather than go
through the different
neurotransmitters, we can think about this
as what, what can you say?
Well some neurons can say yes, yes, yes,
yes.
Some neurons say no, no, no, no.
Some neurons kind of hem and haw before
they say
maybe, probably, or questionable.
So there is a difference in both speed,
whether is something's fast
or slow, or also whether it's affirmative
or or negative.
So yes or no and how, how fast does it
take you to get to yes or no, versus
negative?
Neurons differ in all these various ways
and that's why neurons,
to me, they're as different as all the
stars in the sky.
Everyone's its own, its own self.
In the next segment, we're going to look
at the support staff.
What enables neurons to, to shine like the
stars in the sky?
And, and they need a lot of support and
we'll meet that support staff in
the next segment.