[MUSIC]
So just like any stars, neurons need a lot
of support.
And in fact, the support cells of the, of
the nervous
system are called glial cells, and they
outnumber the
the neurons in number by ten to one, at
least ten to one.
So, there are ten times more glial cells
supporting the stars then there are stars
themselves.
So, the neurons, are a minority of what's
in the nervous system.
And so, let's, let's think about what do
the glial cells do.
Well, the glial cells clean up after the
neurons.
They take all the stuff that the neurons
dump into the extra cellular space,
and they take it up, and they recycle it,
and they prepare it for re-use.
They form the scaffolding that allows
these synpases to form.
They, they maintain these synapses by, by
making
sure that the two, that the synaptic
terminal and the neuron
that it's talking to are held tightly
together.
They can't talk across very long distances
and so these, this synapse
is a very delicate structure and it has to
be just so.
And who does that?
Not the neurons.
It's the glial cells that, that do that.
The, the glial cells are also critical to
the development of the nervous system.
Neurons don't get born and move to where
they need to go to without glial cells.
So, glial cells are absolutely, the brain
is, is not going to work without the glial
cells anymore than a city is going to work
without sanitation workers and
all sorts of city support staff.
Okay?
So, the neurons need the glial cells.
There are different types of glial cells,
and we're not going to go
through all of them but we're going to
mention just a few of them.
Astrocytes are the ones that, these are
the most numerous type of glial cells.
And these are cell, glial cells in the
central
nervous system, that are doing all this
cleaning up.
They're doing the cleaning up.
They're doing the scaffolding.
They are the work horses of the central
nervous system.
Then there are two different glial cells
who's job it is
to make myelin and we're going to spend
some time on myelin.
Myelin is an insulating wrap for axons.
And there are two different types of glial
cells that make myelin because one of
them makes it for central neurons, and one
of them makes it for peripheral neurons.
So oligodendrocytes make myelin for
central neurons,
and Schwann cells make myelin for
peripheral neurons.
And we'll come back to that.
So myelin is a, it's a fatty substance
that surrounds the axons.
And what we're going to talk about in the
next segment is what does myelin do that's
so important and why is it a problem, a
big problem, in fact, if we lose myelin?
And, and losing myelin is the
basis for demyelining diseases such
multiple sclerosis.
Okay.
So in the next segment, we'll talk about
myelin.
[MUSIC]