[MUSIC]
So remember that the allele
cells that make the myelin, there
different types
that make it in the central nervous system
and in the peripheral nervous system.
And because of that, people get a
demyelinating disease, get it either in
the central nervous system, or in the
peripheral nervous system, but not in
both.
So the problem is either in the
oligodendrocytes and
that, and the interaction between the
oligodendrocytes and the axon.
In which case, you get a central
Demyelinating disease,
and the most common by far is multiple
sclerosis.
Or, there's a problem in the Schwann cell
and its connection to the axon.
And in that case, you can get a variety,
There are a group of,
a diverse group of hereditar, hereditary
neuropathies called Charcot–Marie–Tooth.
These are Demyelinating diseases that
typically are, they are
inherited and they typically progress and
become worse with time.
There's also an acute demyelinating
disease
called Guillain-Barre which typically has
a very
quick onset, it's inflammatory, and,
luckily, it, it goes away after a while.
So, what are the symptoms?
Well, the symptoms from, it, from our
perspective or the symptoms is that the
neural code is disrupted anywhere there is
Demyelination.
So, the Demyelination in the puriferal
nervous system is mostly going to affect
motor axons, because they conduct at they
transfer information the fastest.
So these are going to have a lot of motor
symptoms, but once we
go to the Central Nervous System, there
are axons all over, there are myelinated
axons all over that do all manner of
things and the symptoms that
a person gets, with Multiple Sclerosis
will
entirely depend on which axons are
affected.
Now there are external groups that are
more typically
effected than others in multiple
Sclerosis, but there is no,
there is no group that's always affected
and there is
no group that's immune from the effects
from multiple Sclerosis.
So the effect of Multiple Sclero,
Sclerosis are
at a basic level to disrupt the neural
code.
But the actual symptoms that will result
from that
disruption, are going to be individual
across, across the group.
Okay, so in the next module, what we're
going to do is
we're going to, clarify this difference
between the central nervous system and
the peripheral nervous system.
[MUSIC]