[MUSIC]
So in this module we're going to meet the
stars of
the nervous system, and the stars of the
nervous system are neurons.
Neurons are really special.
So, admittedly, I am a complete
neuro-chauvinist.
But, I can tell you that, let's say
you've seen ten gastrointestinal cells,
you've seen em all.
Let's say you've seen ten cardiomyocytes,
Ten lung cells, liver cells, kidney cells,
etc.
Kind of pretty standard.
There might five, ten different types but
after that you're, you're out of
variation.
Totally different story in the, in the
department of neurons.
So, neurons are, are basically unique.
You could ca-, if you were a real lumper,
you
could categorize them into maybe a few
million different types.
So, we are going to look at neurons in
some detail.
Before, before we get into their
particular
appearance, let's just understand one of
the features that makes neurons so unique.
And that is that they are the longest,
they can be the longest cell in the body.
So, our longest neuron is a neuron that
has a
process that starts at your big toe and
ends right here.
In me, that's about five feet, one and a
half meters.
In really tall people that can be six
feet, two meters.
So, that's a really long process.
There's no other ce, cell type in the
entire body that is that long or that
large.
Now, in the next segment, what we're
going to do is we're going to get the
vocabulary to understand the, the
individual uniqueness of of neurons.
[MUSIC].