[MUSIC].
There are four parts to neurons.
Neurons have four parts.
The first is the cell body or, or also
called
the soma and this is the part that all
cells have.
This is cell central,there's the nucleus
here with the DNA.
This is like city hall,it's going to give
out all the orders.
There's a manufacturing plant here where
proteins are made.
There is an energy a power plant here,so
this
is really the, the place that keeps the
cell going.
It makes all the, the material for the
entire the entirety of,
of a neuron which can be, as we said in
the last segment, very, very long,very
large,so the cell body has coming out from
it a varie, a number of dendrites
and these dendrites branch and they
continue to branch and they can branch 2,
3, 4, 5 times and so that makes a tree,
which we call the dendritic arbor or the
dendritic tree and, these dendrites are
responsible for gathering in information.
They're the, they're the sentries,they're
the place where, they're
the ears of this, of the cell of the
neuron.
They're taking in all information,so
information, is going into the dendrites
into the cell body to a certain extent,but
really into the dendrites.
So what do we do with all that
information?
Well, the cell is going to, process it,
sum
it up, and then send it out, through one
axon.
There's one axon and while these dendrites
are very local, they're going to have
a, a local distribution, this axon can go
far, far distances
and so, this can go a meter easily,um,
so this is an axon, and it's going to
carry the information a,
along, the length of it,but, then, then
what?
So, you have to get to a terminal, which
is a communications center, which is
going to take that information and give it
to the next cell in line
and if we just blow up this area right
here, what we see is that there's a
synaptic terminal, which is separated by a
space and
then contacts another cell,so the
information transfer
is in this direction, from the axon to the
next
cell and this point of information
transfer is called the synapse.
This cell ,this second cell, the infer,
the,
the cell that the neuron is talking to can
be any of a variety of cell types.
It can be another neuron,so most of the
neurons
in the brain they just talk to other
neurons.
There is a little internal convers, a big
internal conversation going
on there,so neurons talk to neurons but
neurons also go talk to
muscles and neurons talk to glands and
neurons talk to the
cardiac to, to the heart, to the cardiac
muscle,um, and so on.
Okay,in the, in the next segment what
we're going to do is look at the variety
uh,I've drawn one cell and this but cells
look really different even
in the same place, they look really
different and we'll look at some of
the variety of, of neurons and talk a
little bit more about their uniqueness.
[MUSIC]