[MUSIC]
So, we're going to talk now about the
difference between
the Central Nervous System and the
Peripheral Nervous System.
There's a barrier,there's a fence, and
that
fence is the demarcation between central
and peripheral.
And that fence is made up of three
membranes, and those three membranes are
the meninges.
There are three meningeal layers, and the
three layers
go from very weak, very tender, the pia,
to very
tough, the dura and, in between, there's a
spidery
thing called the arachnoid, a spidery
layer called the arachnoid.
So, let's just look at what that looks
like.
We're only going to see the arachnoid in,
in this next picture.
So here, this is the brain, and what's
covering the brain here, up here
is pia and you can't see it, it's so thin,
and so tender that we don't see it.
But in this view, the dura has been
removed and now we're looking down on this
film, it's a, it's an actual membrane, and
that membrane is the arachnoid.
So, the different meningeal layers have
different purposes, different functions.
The dura is the, is a tough sack, and that
is
what's going to keep us from having
concussions all the time.
All right, so it's going to float our
brain in in fluid
and prevent it from banging about, and,
and actually getting bruised.
It takes a hard hit to actually injure the
brain,
and hopefully we, we don't have, we don't
incur that.
Okay, so the meninges go from, pia is
closest to the central nervous
system, is closest to the brain and spinal
cord, and then dura is farthest away.
And their, all the neurons, almost all of
the neurons in the central nervous
system, 200 billion minus something less
than
100,000 are contained completely within
the central neurons.
The only neurons that leave the central
nervous system,
are these neurons that, that serve a motor
function.
They actually go out the meninges and they
go into the periphery.
In the periphery, there's the peripheral
nervous system,
and there's also every, the rest of the
body.
So there are motor neurons, they go to
skeletal muscle, the
voluntary muscle, so that we can move our
arms and our legs.
And these are motor neurons.
And then there are Motor neurons that go
to Autonomic Neurons that control our
glands, that controls the cardiac muscle,
they control our gut, smooth muscle.
So for instance, these are going to be,
these neurons are what is
going to be active when you see food and
you start to salivate.
Well, somebody's got to tell that gland to
start salivating and
it's the brain and it does it through this
two neuron chain.
So, those are Autonomic Neurons.
In addition to the motor neurons that
carry information from the
central nervous system to the peripheral
nervous system, there are sensory neurons.
And these sensory neurons are peripheral.
They are located peripherally, and they
carry information into the central nervous
system.
What you'll note is we call a neuron
either
or sensorial or peripheral based on where
the cell body
is not based on where its axon is or
its dendrites, but based on where the cell
body is.
So these Peripheral Neurons include
Sensory Neurons and
Autonomic Neurons, these are in the
autonomic ganglia.
The consequence of that is that these
neurons share vulnerabilities.
The, the, they share with each other but
not with the central neurons.
So, for example, there's a disease called
Congenital insensitivity to pain.
People with this disease suffered a
mutation in
one of a number of developmental,
developmentally important genes.
And what it did was it, it, prevented a
group of sensory neurons
from developing, those sensory neurons
that respond to injury.
So, these people are insensitive, they
never
feel pain, because they can't, they don't
have
the sensory neurons that will respond to
noxious
stimulation which is what usually brings
us pain.
But in addition, there's a group of
the Autonomic Neurons that also
developmentally got
knocked out, and these are the neurons
that lead you to be able to sweat.
And so, people with Congenital
insensitivity to pa, to
pain often have what's called anhydrous,
meaning they can't sweat.
Those seem like two completely weird
symptoms to put
together, but they're not weird because
they make complete sense.
Both of them are due to a
developmental abnormality in the
peripheral nervous system.
So, in the next segment what we're
going to do is, is look again, look a
little bit more closely at other diseases
that preferentially affect either the
periphery or the central nervous system.
[MUSIC]