[MUSIC]
So the approach that we're
going to use in this course is to use
Bobby's story, to
organize our consideration of
neurobiology.
So, we're going to look at perception, and
then we're going to look at motor
function, and
then we're going to look at homeostasis,
and
then we're going to look at higher
abstract functions.
Before we get to that, we're going to
spend the
first, the, the next three weeks, getting
some vocabulary.
So, making sure that we can use the same
words and we can understand each other.
So we're going to go through how do
neurons
talk to each other, we're going to
understand about neuroanatomy.
We're going to understand the basics, how
the brain and spinal cord develop.
And then, how they actually are organized
in the adult.
And then, we're going to look at what goes
wrong in
the central nervous system, and we're
going to focus on strokes.
After we have that vocabulary, and our
basic understanding of how the
brain is structured both physiologically
and anatomically, we are going to go into
topics, and the first topic is we're
going to look at perception and
we are going to use two pers, perceptual
modalities to look at this.
We are going to look at vision, and we are
going to look at hearing.
There are other perceptions that we have,
obviously, touch and the stimuli
sense, taste and smell and we are not
going to talk about those.
We have to pick and choose here.
So we are going to look at vision and
hearing,
pro, arguably the two most important
senses for humans.
Then we are going to talk about how we
control voluntary movement.
And we're going to divide this into two
different units, one where we're going to
talk about the hierarchy that gets us from
essentially from polio to a stroke.
So, how do you move a muscle?
How do you actually make an intentional
movement
such as, raising your hand or moving your
hand?
And then we're going to go into the, the
modulatory part of, of movement.
How do we organize?
How do we coordinate movement?
How do we make movements go faster?
How do we make them habitual movements?
So then we'll spend a unit on that, as
well.
Then we'll move on to homeostatis, we're
going to
look at how mothers become bonded to their
children.
How that works when they give birth, and
when they're nursing, we'll look at
thermal regulation and breathing, voiding
urine and
we will look at the sleep wake cycle.
So these are all things that we have to
do, to stay alive, we have to do
and they are supported by both automatic
and intentional movements.
And finally, we'll end up with executive
function, or
higher abstract function, and here we'll
focus on emotions.
We'll focus mostly on emotions and memory,
and
we'll end up talking about how we can play
well with others, and the challenges that
are
that playing well with others presents to
the brain.
Okay, so I hope to see you next week.
[MUSIC]