[MUSIC]
So we are going to talk about brain
tumors.
But before we talk about brain tumors,
let's talk about the basics of cancer.
In cancer there is a primary tumor.
So let's say that you have a, a tumor in
your colon.
That means that a colon cell is dividing,
and dividing,
and dividing, and instead of stopping, it
keeps on dividing.
It becomes immortal.
It's just going to divide without any
limits.
And because it keeps on dividing, it keeps
on growing, it gets bigger and bigger.
And if that's all that were going to
happen, that would
be okay, because we'd go in, and we'd take
it out.
But that's not all that happens.
What happens in cancer is that, that one
of those cells decides to
go rogue, or few of those cells decide to
go rogue and they travel some place else.
And then they start a new tumor elsewhere.
So they metastasize.
They spread.
So, the cell that or tumor starts in the
colon, and then
a few cells float off to some other place,
and now all of
a sudden, you've got tumors that are in
your bones, or tumors
that are in your lungs, and maybe even a
tumor in your brain.
Same thing with breast cancer or lung
cancer,
it starts in one place, it starts in
the breast or it starts in the lung, but
from there it can spread to other organs.
So, one source of brain tumors is
metastasis spreads from
other or, from other tumors, so for
instance lung tumors.
The metastasis are a problem and actually
the brain tumors are a problem because
they exist within the cranium, and the
cranium is a fixed, bony container.
It can't expand.
And as a tumor expands, the, the cranium
is not going to expand.
It's going to increase the pressure and
we're going to have a problem.
Okay, so besides having tumors that spread
from other
organs, what are the other sources of
brain tumors?
Well, one of the very consistent things
about neurons is that they don't divide.
They are what's called, they are, they are
at the end of their line.
They have no descendants.
Once a neuron is born, it lives and it
dies and when it dies, that's the end.
It doesn't, it cannot replace itself, and,
and that's the end.
So neurons don't make tumors because they
don't divide
at all, and they don't get into this
uncontrolled division.
So what makes tumors?
Well, it's other cell types within the
brain.
And the primary one that does this are
glial cells.
So glial cells don't have the limits on
division that neurons do.
So, glial cells can divide and make these
tumors.
And and so, glials, gliomas, tumors of
glial
cells, are the most common type of brain
tumor.
Another type of brain tumor are,
is the type that comes from a division
of meningeal cells, and these are called
meningiomas.
Remember that we have the pia, the
arachnoid, and the dura.
These are meningeal cells that cover the
brain and if they start to divide
once again they're going to make a
space-occupying
tumor that's going to increase pressure
within the skull.
And finally, the other major type of brain
tumor
is are tumors that come from glandular
cells.
Now, you might think, well, the glandular
cells, I've
got glands here, and I've got glands under
my armpit.
I've got glands at various places.
But do I really have glands in my head?
Well, it turns out you have two glands in
your head.
One is right here, and that one is called
the pineal gland.
You may have heard it, heard of it,
because it makes melatonin.
Melatonin might help you sleep.
And the pineal gland is, is important for
the daily rhythm of, of waking and
sleeping.
And this, these glandular cells are not
neurons.
They're, they're gland cells, and they can
become, they can divide without, without
control.
The other, gland that we have in our head
is, is one that sits right here.
It's not actually on this picture, but
it's called the pituitary,
and these pituitary cells can also divide
and that's called pituitary adenomas.
These pituitary adenomas are fairly
common.
They account for about 10 to 25% of
inter-cranial tumors.
Okay, so bottom line is, brain tumors are
a problem because they take up space.
Brain tumors are not tumors of neurons,
they're
tumors of glial cells, meningeal cells, or
glandular
cells, or they are metastasis spread from
other
organs such as the colon or the lung.
Okay.
That's it for this week.
I, I bet you've learned a lot!
In the next segment, I'm going to
introduce the topics
that we're going to cover in the rest of
this course.
[MUSIC]