[MUSIC]
So, the difference between the peripheral
and the central nervous system, is
important.
It's incredibly important because the
diseases.
That affect the nervous system, affect
either peripheral or central nervous
system.
They don't tend to affect both.
They're very few.
And the meninges form a very effective
barrier against.
Toxins, against viruses, against all sorts
of damage, so that the peripheral nervous
system tends to be far more vulnerable,
than is the central nervous system.
In addition, the two regions have very
different capacities for repair.
If you cut a, an axon in the peripheral
nervous system, it can repair itself.
It will reconnect.
If there's a traumatic injury to the
central nervous system that does not
happen.
So, the ability to repair is far, far
greater
in the periphery than in, in the central
nervous system.
And ever since I was a graduate student in
the early 80s,
this has been a topic that people have
been very interested in.
They've been trying to make the central
environment
more hospitable to repair, more like the
peripheral environment.
This is something that, this is a, a, a
research
area that's had some successes but is,
presents an ongoing challenge.
And the truth is that today we still have
not achieved
the ability to regenerate or repair within
the central nervous system.
So let's, let's look at some of the
Ways in which the peripheral nervous
system is vulnerable.
So, it's vulnerable to say a, large
molecules such as botulinum toxin.
So, botulinum toxin which comes from
spoiled food can get in and it
primarily will effect these peripheral, it
will only effect these peripheral neurons.
It will not get past the meninges.
Let's take another example which is
viruses and so.
When there is a, one of the viruses is
polio.
And polio virus, actually gets in right
here at this
synapse between the motor neuron and the
voluntary muscle, and it goes back.
It travels back and see, it did a clever
thing.
It got through the meninges.
But it got through the meninges by getting
in through this the axon of this motor
neuron.
And what does it do in return?
For thanks, it actually kills this motor
neuron.
So now, this motor neuron is going to die.
And there, therefore, there is going to be
weakness or an inability
to move that muscle that was infected with
the polio virus.
Let's look at another virus herpes zoster,
and herpes
zoster is a virus that, that produces
what's commonly called as shingles.
And in herpes zoster, the, the virus gets
in here, it gets transported back inside
the
cell, inside the axon in these sensory
neurons,
and then it goes and lives in here.
And if all is great, all is well.
It lives in there and then it never talks
again.
But, under some circumstances, the virus
can decide to
reproduce and blossom, and it will make so
many copies of
itself that it actually sends it back out
that way, and what you get is.
A virus all throughout the sensory
territory, and what you get is a rash.
So this is the skin, the sensory neuron
has a process
that ends in the skin, it takes up this
herpes zoster.
This zoster lives in the cell body, but if
there's an outbreak, it will send
all these virus particles back out to the
skin and you'll get a rash.
And here is an example of somebody who has
a rash.
Now, let's notice a couple things about
it.
First of all, it's only on one side.
Because the infection is only on one
side and,and these sensory neurons, are,
are going to
obey the midline perfectly, so it, the
other half of the face is completely
unaffected.
The other thing that you notice, is that
it's, it's in this distribution, and
this distribution is one of the most
common places to have shingles.
The common place is in the thoracic region
right about here.
So and this is a distribution
that has an anatomical basis.
This is the ophthalmic division of the
trigeminal nerve.
Luckily, this does go away.
And, it did go away for this individual.
So, another, another example that's more
like botulinum toxin is sarin.
Sarin is a big molecule.
And it's only going to affect the
periphery.
It's not going to affect the central
nervous system.
In the next segment, we're going to talk
about brain tumors.
[MUSIC]