[MUSIC]
Okay.
So in this unit, we're going to talk about
how neurons talk to each other.
Before we examine how they talk to each
other.
We have to figure out how they talk,
period.
And you, you could say, and I think that
most people understand that neurons talk
by using electrical signals.
So you could say they, they tru, they talk
electrical-ese.
But there's a really key difference
between the electrical
language of a neuron or of any living
cell.
And the electrical language of one of your
devices,
one of your electrical devices at home or
here.
So in, in an appliance in something that
you
plug into the wall, what we're using is
just electrons.
In the living organism, we don't use
electrons.
Instead, we use molecules that have a
charge and those molecules are called
ions.
So, ions are simply molecules where the
number
of protons is not equal to the number of
electrons.
Another way to think about this is, these
molecules have either, lost an electron or
two.
Oops, lost that electron.
And now they're positively charged.
Or they've gained one.
One has come on to this, this molecule.
And then they're negatively charged.
So ions are either positively charged or
negatively
charged, just because they've either
gained or lost, electrons.
So these, these ions,
are present within the context of cells.
And cells all have what are called
cellular membranes.
So a membrane is a, is a very amazing
structure that's made up mostly of fat.
It's important to understand that most of
a membrane is fat.
And this is like a layer of oil surrounded
by a couple layers of water.
So here's inside the cell.
Here's outside the cell.
I've only detailed a small part of this.
But this would continue all the way around
the cell.
So, if I have a charged particle.
Let's consider an ion that's positively
charged.
And let's consider, consider one that's
potassium.
So, K plus equals a potassium ion.
Well, this potassium ion is very happy in
water.
But it can't get through oil.
It's not going to pass through there.
So, it's going to bounce off this
membrane.
And the only way for it to get through, is
via
a special place, which is, which we're
going to call an ion channel.
Okay.
So, this is nothing, more fancy than
essentially a cat door for the potassium
ion.
This is a door.
This is the building.
And this is the only way in or out.
You cannot go through the walls.
You gotta go through a door.
And the door is called an ion channel.
[COUGH] Now, how is the potassium going to
distribute across this membrane?
Well, the potassium has two [COUGH]
features.
One is a chemical.
It's, it's a molecule.
So, as a, as a chemical it's akin
to a food dye.
So, if I put a lot of blue dye here, and
there's no
blue dye here, well, the blue dye is going
to go that way.
Because the gradient is there's more here
than there.
In the end, if there's an open door, the
amount of blue dye everywhere is going to
be even.
So, the chemical force for this potassium
ion is to leave.
Leave the cell.
But, on the other hand, this, the cell is
actually negatively charged.
And outside, this is 0.
It's, it's, it's like being ground.
It's grounded.
It's got a lightning rod there.
So, this is negatively charged and this is
0.
Well, the potassium ion is positive.
And so there's an electrical force that
goes inside the cell.
So, what, what happens?
Well, you, you cannot reason your way
through this.
But very smart, physical chemists and
physicists worked out, how this went.
At what potential the chemical force and
the electrical force will be even.
And that is where the membrane is going to
sit.
Where the chemical force and the
electrical force are
even for every ion that we have to worry
about.
And we have to worry about three ions, the
potassium ion,
the sodium ion, which is also positively
charged, and chloride ion.
And once we take into consideration each
of these ions, what we see is that this
cell is going to sit at rest at about
negative 70 to negative 60 mV.
Millivolts being 1 1,000th of a volt.
Now we, all the time, we have batteries
that give us nine volts or a few volts.
Anyway, this is 1 1000th of a volt.
That doesn't sound like a lot of potential
voltage.
But you're talking about keeping it across
a, a very small distance.
And so, this is essentially like keeping a
lightning bolt an inch away from yourself.
This is a very an amazing structure.
It's a very powerful structure.
So, the bottom line is that at rest, what
we have is a distribution of these
different ions.
Based on their electrical and their
chemical, based on electrical and chemical
forces.
And, the result is, that this neuron is
going to
sit always at a negative potential, until
something happens.
And, that's what we're going to talk about
in the next segment.
[MUSIC]