[MUSIC]
So what we talked about in the last
segment was how neurons sit at, at
a resting membrane potential of about
negative 65 millivolts.
And through mechanisms that we're going to
come to.
That resting membrane potential is just
sort of the
it's the potential around which the neuron
oscillates.
So, at, at one point it might get an input
that.
If this is 0, that brings it closer to
0 or takes it farther away from 0, et
cetera.
And these small little potential
differences, which are on the
order of less than one millivolt up to,
say, five millivolts.
These small, little potential differences,
can travel, along the neuron.
If this is, if these are the dendrites
and, and here's an axon.
They might travel, but they're going to
peter out pretty quickly.
So, it's not a a useful it's not going to
work to simply rely on these small
potential changes.
Now if we have to go long distances.
Now, one of the things that is so
different about a neuron than
any other cell type in the body is that we
are, that these neurons.
We [LAUGH] meet a neuron.
Neurons are very long.
Okay.
So think about a heart cell.
A heart cell is so big, it's contained in
the heart, it ain't going anywhere,
besides the heart.
A pancreatic cell is sitting in the
pancreas, it's in the pancreas.
It's pretty small.
A lung cell, et cetera.
Now, let's think about the longest neuron
that we posses.
The longest neuron that we possess is a
cell that has a cell body right here.
And it sends one process all the way down
to the toe, and it
sends another process all the way up to
the medulla.
So, depending on how tall this person is.
In me, that's a, one and a half meters,
say, so five feet or something like that.
But in a very tall person, or even in
a very short person, that's still a lot of
feet.
That's feet long.
So, a small potential like one millivolt
or five millivolts is not going to travel.
If that's what we had to rely on, just
moving from here
to here, the message, any message that
started here would end there.
It just wouldn't get there.
It wouldn't get to where it needs to go.
It needs to go here.
And so, in order to, to communicate within
neurons,
because neurons are so long, we use
something called the Action Potential.
And the Action Potential, in contrast to
being this, this kind of small thing, is.
It goes really far up and comes back down,
so it's
about 100 millivolts in, in height.
So from the resting memory potential to
the top of the
Action Potential, which happens at around
plus say, 20 millivolts or so.
It's, we're talking about roughly 100
millivolts of, of difference.
And that can get communicated all the way
up.
That's not going to get lost.
And what carries that Action Potential, is
that.
Remember that we, we, we looked at
potassium being very
high in a cell and much lower outside a
cell.
Well, the reverse is true for sodium.
And so, the sodium comes flooding in, and
because it's positively charged,
that's what takes the, the cell up to this
very high memory potential.
Now the the ability for, for a neuron to
communicate from
here to here using an Action Potential is,
it can do that.
But that'll be a slow process unless we
add
one more thing, and that is a, an
insulator,
essentially a very nice insulator called
myelin.
[MUSIC]