Let's have a
little primer
for those of you who may
have forgotten some of these terms, what
various electrical terms mean.
And so, let's consider
the water analogy.
In fact, electricity is very much like
water for a lot of the terms.
So, let's consider that we, we have a
landscape that's very flat.
And there's a there's a river, or creek,
that's sitting here.
If this is flat is the water going
anywhere?
Not so much.
Because it, all of this water.
Is at the same level, and at the same
level, it has the same potential.
And so, if the potential is, it, if
there's no
difference in their potential, then there
is also no current.
But now let's imagine that we come up here
and we have a, an, a waterfall.
[SOUND] Now, there's going to be flow,
because we have a potential drop.
This has a higher potential than this has.
And water is going to go down.
And you're going to have a current.
This, this potential drop will, will,
drive the current.
Okay, and then consider what would happen
eh, if we had a higher waterfall.
Well, this would have a greater potential
than this would and we would have
more of a drop, more of a potential
difference and a higher current.
One last thing to consider If, if we now
look down on this, and
we push this water through a, an opening
that is this big.
Versus an opening that is.
This big.
What have we changed?
Well, we've changed the resistance.
Here, there's more resistance.
And so, the, the amount of water that goes
through there is going to be reduced.
The current is going to be reduced here.
And it will be greater in this larger
channel.
Electricity is just like that.
And the things that we have to worry
about when it comes to neuronal
communication is potential.
So, potential in this context means
what's the potential difference from
inside the cell to outside the cell,
and it's, it's negative, we'll say
negative 65 millivolts.
It varies, but around negative 65
millivolts.
And remember that a millivolt is one one
thousandth of a volt
and the, another thing
that we have to worry about is that we
remember that there are ion channels
that go and, and provide a way for ions to
go in and out of a cell
And as they go in and out of the cell,
they are carrying current.
And finally, this whole cell has a
resistance.
If none, none of the channels are open,
the resistance is very high, infinite.
But if there are, let's say, three
channels open, the resistance is high,
but it's and it's much lower if we now
open say 100 channels.
Okay?
So, those are the, within the context of a
neuron that's what we mean
when we talk about potential, there's
potential
difference across the membrane, across
this, from the
inside of the cell to the outside of the
cell, there's current that goes
through ion channels, and there is a
resistance between the inside of the cell
and
the outside of the cell.
[MUSIC]