[MUSIC]
Okay, so we
have an action potential coming down the
line, down the axon, and we have.
Neurotransmitters that are packaged within
vesicles.
How we get those, the neurotransmitter out
of the vesicle and across,
out of the cell and able to go and effect
another cell.
Well to understand this we have to realize
that.
There is a, there's a cell membrane, but
the cell
also has a lot of other membranes that are
inside.
Inside in these things called organelles.
So, for instance, there's a nuclear
envelope and nuclear membrane.
There are mitochondria.
These are the power houses of the cell.
There is endoplasmic particulum where all
the proteins are
made so the manufacturing cell center of
the cell.
There are endosomes and lysosomes, which
are basically the garbage
collectors of the cell, and all of these
are surrounded by.
Membranes.
And so, in order and there are vesicles
that traffic the
proteins from the endoplasmic reticulum
out to the appropriate place.
So, some proteins are going to go to the
membranes.
Some are going to go to these other
places.
So
the fusion between two different
membranes,
between say the endoplasmic reticulum
membrane and
the membrane of a vesicle that's going to
traffic a protein to some place.
That happens all the time.
It happens constitutively.
And so our challenge, as a neuron, is to
stop that.
We can't have these vesicles fusing with
the
plasma membrane, with the cell membrane
all the time.
That would be, that would not.
Work, what we want to do is we want to
make the
vesicle fuse to the membrane only when the
action potential arrives.
So the key to neurotransmitter release is
two things.
Number one, we're going to suppress
constitutive release.
Suppress constitutive or ongoing release
and
number two, we are going to link the
release that we want.
We are going to link release in the
synaptic terminal to the action potential.
So we are going to link release.
To the action potential.
And the way that we do that, first of all
there
is a molecule that suppresses constitutive
release within the synaptic terminal.
So that's great, so that's done.
Now let's think about how do we link
release to the action potential.
Well, when the action potential comes
down, this the membrane
potential, remember that the membrane
potential, if this is zero ground,
the membrane potential's around negative
65 millivolts.
But.
In comes that action potential, and it
goes skyrocketing, and as
this potential increases, it opens a
particular type of ion channel that
lets in a for, we haven't talked about
this ion, but it's a very important ion.
It let's in calcium ions.
These are positively charged, they lost,
oops, forgot two
electrons, so they've got a, a two
positive charges.
And, these calcium ions are going to flood
in to
the synaptic terminal, and that is going
to trigger release.
The release that happens.
Of vesicles that contain neurotransmitters
is
only happens when the calcium
concentration increases.
And the calcium concentration only
increases when the action potential
arrives.
So now we have accomplished our goal.
We suppressed the constitutive release and
now we've,
we've linked the release to the action
potential.
And all that happens when the calcium
concentration increases is that this
vesicular membrane and the the cell
membrane.
They actually,.
They're not just close, they fuse and so
you get something that looks like this.
Calcium comes in and now these two touch
and then it looks something like this.
It opens, this joins and it opens and then
that goes
to a bigger opening and then they're just,
it's all one.
So now we've released neurotransmitter but
the
key point was that we didn't particularly
release, it's not like we pumped it out,
we simply fused the vesicle membrane.
To the cell membrane.
In the next segment we're going to look at
a very important drug that affects this
process.
[MUSIC]