[MUSIC]
Okay, so we left
off with action potential.
So we've got a message going from one end
of a cell to another end of a
cell, and now we're going to get that
message
across to another cell through something
called a synapse.
But the this like, so, so getting the
action potential is like
I have breathed out all this air, and now
I just have to form
my lips to, to make sound, but in the case
of the neuron.
This neuron is obviously not talking in
sound.
It's talking in chemistry.
It's talking in things like
neurotransmitters.
And neurotransmitters, are a list of, or a
number of molecules.
They serve other functions in the body,
but
they also serve very critical functions
for the
nervous system as neurotransmitters, as
the things that
that communicate from one neuron to
another neuron.
And what we're going to look at right now,
is how neurotransmitters are made and how
they're packaged.
So this is a drawing of a cell, here's the
cell body, the nucleus
with the DNA, here are some mitochondria,
this is the powerhouse of the cell.
The endoplasmic reticulum, which is
essentially the
manufacturing centre of the cell where
proteins
are made, and then we have an axon which
leads down to a synaptic terminal.
And this synaptic terminal has these
entities
here, which are called synaptic vesicles
and they're small little, organelles.
They're little vesicles, they, they're
made of a
membrane, just like the, the cell is, has
a,
has a cell membrane, these vesicles have a
vesicular
membrane, and if we look at one of these.
So it has a membrane, remember that the
membrane looks
something like this but we're not going to
draw that all.
So here's the membrane, and inside here is
neurotransmitter.
Is a, is a neurotransmitter.
And, the neurotransmitter can be any
number
of of a number of different molecules.
Here are just a few of them Glutamate,
GABA, Serotonin, Dopamine, Acetylcholine.
There's a more complete list that you can
see and the
only other thing I want to add is, why is
this important?
Why is it important?
Well, first of all, it's important that
the neurotransmitters are packaged
in, is vesicles and that'll be important
in, in a moment.
The second thing that's important about
this is that we can use this.
We can use the synthesis of a
neurotransmitter
as a, as a, as a therapeutic tool.
So, for instance Dopamine is missing in
Parkinsons disease.
It's not that dopamine isn't made per say,
that's there's a problem with making it.
It's that the cells that make it die.
So, or, or a group of the cells that do
make Dopamine die, and so what do you do
about that?
Well it turns out that there's something
called Mass
Effect which means, that you take the
starting chemical.
The, the, the substrate.
What we call the substrate and then
through a series of enzymatic
Processes reaction through a series of
enzymatic reactions, we end up with a
neurotransmitter and in the case of
Dopamine,
in Parkinson's there is lack of Dopamine
and what happ,
what do we do to treat in most people
Parkinson's.
We give them the substrate, and so that is
what Sinemet
which is also in, in other countries
called Parcopa.
so, th-, these are drugs that provide a
lot
of this, and even if only a little bit of
this gets made, much less
than what you start with, it's more than
what the, the person
has, and it enables them, it, it
alleviates their symptoms of Parkinson's.
So you flood the system with substrate,
and the goal is
to get a little bit of that
neurotransmitter out of the system.
Okay.
So that's how we're going to speak what's
coming
out of the neurons mouth, so to speak.
Is not sound, but neurotransmitter.
Neurotransmitter that is packaged in
vesicles, and in
the next segment we are going too see how.
How it actually gets out of the mouth.
[MUSIC]