[MUSIC]
Okay, so let's talk about botox.
Botox is one of the, one of
several clostridial toxins, made by
clostridial bacteria.
And the full name of Botox is actually
botulinum toxin.
And to understand what botulinum toxin
does, we need to know one more thing.
We, what I told you is that the vesicles
are, are held very close to the cell
membrane.
What holds them?
A group of three proteins.
Two of them anchored in the cell membrane,
one of them
anchored in the vesicle membrane the
details don't matter as much.
But this complex is called the Snare
Complex.
And what happens is that when calcium
comes in.
It changes its shape.
It changes its conformation.
And it goes from, doing like that to being
in a straight line.
So that pushes the vesicle into the plasma
membrane and fusion is inevitable.
Resistance is futile.
So you have to, at that point, when
they're that close, they have to fuse.
It takes a lot of energy for them not to
fuse, and when they're that close,
there's, it, it, it's inevitable.
Okay, so, it's this snare pin, and it's
the
snare pin's sensitivity to calcium that is
the final event that
allows the vesicle to fuse with the cell
membrane.
Botox comes in and cuts any one of these
well, Botox cuts a particular one.
But the clostridial toxins cut a variety
of places
in these three proteins that make up the
snare pin.
If the snare pin is broken, for whatever
reason, if that is cut then release
doesn't happen.
And it's as simple as that.
So, what, what the clostridial toxins are
doing is blocking release.
Now, if you block release, if somebody is
administered
a sufficient dose of botulinum toxin, the
release
that we have to care about is the release
from a motor neuron to the diaphragm.
The diaphragm is the thing that allows us
to breathe.
Diaphragm is a muscle right here, right in
there.
And we need our diaphragm to contract and
without the diaphragm, we don't breathe.
Without breathing, we don't get oxygen to
our brain.
And without oxygen in the brain, we're
going to die.
So, so, it's a deadly weapon.
And when I first started teaching, in, in,
1992 or in the 90s
we used to talk about the fact that the
clostridial toxins were potential
weapons of, of, of mass destruction, so to
speak.
So, [COUGH]
mass death, anyway.
So now we use them all the time.
And we use them for very serious problems
things like focal dystonia.
Where there is a a, a, a in, inappropriate
continual contraction of a muscle.
And that, it's a basal ganglia disorder.
There are a lot of famous people that have
had, have focal dystonia.
Leon Fleisher is a piano player who has
it, in, in his right hand.
So these two fingers are, are always
contracted.
And Diane Rehm has it in her larynx.
So she has laryngeal focal dystonia.
And these people are treated with Botox.
So the Botox is injected at a very low
dose at a very local, very locally.
So, it's blocking the contraction of these
two fingers in the Leon Fleishers example.
And in the larynx, it's blocking the
cont, spasmodic contraction of the
laryngeal muscles.
So, and it's used for a large variety of
of, of treatments, of various disorders.
It's also used cosmetically.
And the interesting thing about its use in
cosmetics is that I don't think
that we fully understood, before the
widespread use of Botox.
That, we make our own, we make our own
wrinkles.
And there's a lovely quote about how smile
lines are
really great, because they show us how
much we've been smiling.
In fact, we are making our wrinkles, and
what Botox is doing
is preventing the motor neuron from
releasing the neurotransmitter onto the
muscle.
And thereby preventing us from actively
making our own wrinkles.
okay.
So we've gotten our transmitter release.
And now what we're going to talk about is,
is how, we, we've started our
expression, we've started our sends, and
now we have to stop our sends.
So we're going to talk about termination
of the signal
that comes out of the neuron in the next
segment.
[MUSIC]