[MUSIC]
So, in this unit,
what we've seen is how one neuron can
formulate a message.
Formulate a message in terms of action
potentials and send
that message on to another cell which can
receive the message.
And if, and that is a fascinating topic.
And yet, if we knew all the details,
everything that we ever could wish
to know about how, for instance,
neurotransmitter release occurs.
If we knew every single detail, it would
not tell us what
would happen if one of i, i, if the system
failed.
Let's put it another way.
Think about a demyelinating disease.
If we knew everything about how myelin
formed
and everything about how it, it fell
apart,
it wouldn't tell us what are going to be
the symptoms in a person with say,
multiple sclerosis.
Because the symptoms depend not on the
particular
pathophysiology of how the myelin far,
falls apart.
It depends on which neurons are affected.
And so, now we have to take our knowledge
about neuronal communication and
put it within the context of the
incredible complexity of neuroanatomy.
It depends on which neurons are affected.
And so, we're going to look at
neuroanatomy.
We're going to look at what does the brain
do.
What does the brain stem do?
What is the spinal cord?
How does the peripheral how does
information come in from
the periphery and go out, back out to the
muscles?
And that's what we'll do in the next unit.
[MUSIC]