[MUSIC]
Okay so we've almost come full circle.
Now we've released a message from the
presynaptic terminal and the, the issue
here,
the, the next hurdle is to make
sure that the postsynaptic cell receives
that message.
And it receives it.
Through a type of protein.
These are actually multi-protein complexes
called receptors and
receptors are going to populate this
post-synaptic
membrane so that as the neurotransmitter
makes its way across.
The synaptic cleft, some portion of it,
that which is not either diffused away,
taken back up through reuptake, or
degraded through enzymatic degradation.
So the, the survivors will actually make
it over to these receptors.
Now let's just take a look at what the
receptors look like.
Here's the cell membrane.
And these are trans-membrane protein
complexes.
And they form an actual pore.
And through this pore the ions can, can
travel.
So the potassium ions can go out.
The sodium ions can come in.
Chloride ions can come in.
Things like that.
So normally, these receptors are closed,
ions can't come in.
But when a neurotransmitter binds to the
receptor or a couple of neurotransmitter
molecules bind to the receptor, the
receptor's now going to open.
And the pore becomes available for as a
highway for the ions to travel along.
And which way they travel depends on the
type of receptor.
And so, as it turns out, we have two basic
classes of receptors.
There are receptors that we, that have an
excitatory an, effect.
And so, once again, if we return to our,
our cell,
which is sitting at negative 65
millivolts.
We, any receptor, that takes the membrane
potential
closer to zero, and closer to this magical
place that is the threshold for an action
potential.
If you go closer to that, that's an
excitatory receptor.
On the other hand, if there is a a, a
receptor
that actually takes the membrane potential
away
from zero, makes it even more negative.
Then this is taking us away from the
threshold for the action potential.
And so that is an inhibitory,
receptor.
So they come in two flavors, and, the
most ubiquitous excitatory receptor is a
glutamate receptor.
And the most ubiquitous inhibitory
receptor is a GABA receptor.
The neutrotransmitter involved is the same
thing.
So the neutrotransmitter involved in the,
that binds to the
inhibitory GABA receptor is a GABA recept,
is a GABA molecule.
And the neurotransmitter that binds to
the excitatory glutamate receptor is
glutamate.
Okay, so that's how these, these receptors
receive the message.
and, and they integrate all this incoming
information to either.
Make it more likely for them to fire an
action potential or less likely to fire an
action potential.
If they're more likely, if this cell has
an action potential, and it results in
this cell also firing an action potential,
then we've got a game of telephone.
A tag.
And that's, that's how the, the nervous
system, and that's how communication
between neurons happens.
Throughout the, the nervous system.
Now let's, let's think about, what impact
these receptors have on disease and
therapeutics.
So, one impact is there are diseases where
we lose
these receptors and one such disease is
called myasthenia gravis.
We mentioned this in the last segment.
So in myasthenia gravis, let's walk over
here to this lovely image.
[COUGH] this is a, an image from a human.
Here is a motoneuron synaptic terminal.
And you can see these little synaptic
vesicles.
Okay?
And so all those synaptic vesicles contain
acetyl choline, which we will abbreviate
as ACh.
And over here is the muscle.
The muscle is a very, it, it has
this convoluted appearance where it has
these folds.
And it, it doesn't, that doesn't
particularly matter.
But what you see in black, all this black,
these are acetylcholine receptors.
And the acetylcholine has to make it
across
this cleft to get to the acetylcholine
receptors.
In myasthenia gravis, there are antibodies
that, that the body makes.
Unfortunately, by mistake, against these
acetyl, acetyl choline receptors.
And so the antibodies.
Destroy the acetyl receptors, the muscle
doesn't eat,
either has fewer or they're just not
concentrated.
And therefore this this signal is sent
from the motor neuron terminal, but it's
not
received by the muscle, and so at again,
as we talked about in the last segment.
What do we do about that?
Well we, we rely on the fact that there
are a few acetylcholine receptors that
have escaped being killed by the
antibodies and
so we just try and boost this signal.
We know that the motor neuron terminal can
release acetylcholine and now we're
going to stop degradation.
We're going to give an
acetylcholinesterase inhibitor to try
and keep the acetylcholine around longer
so that it
can find its way to the few remaining
acetylcholine receptors and that's a, a
pretty effective therapeutic.
The other therapeutic, obviously that
people with mycenia gravis
get is, let's, let's dampen down that
immune system,
so that you're not making all those
antibodies so
that the acetylcholine receptors won't be
won't be degraded.
And so there's immuno suppressants that
are given to these patients as well.
[MUSIC]