[MUSIC]
Okay, so what we just talked about was
release and
that is release of neurotransmitter that
is packaged
into synaptic vesicles from the synaptic
terminal.
Well, the synaptic terminal is, the point
of that
is to get a message across to a second
cell.
That's the post synaptic cell.
This meeting is the synapse.
And these two neurons [COUGH] this, this
cell
with the synaptic terminal, which is the
pre-synaptic
cell and the post-synaptic cell, they are
separated
by a short distance called the synaptic
cleft.
And the molecules of neurotransmitter are
going to make their way
over to here where they are going to be
received.
That, we'll talk about that in the final
segment.
But the, but what we're going to talk
about
right now is the fact that as you send
this message out, as the synaptic terminal
sends this
message out, it has to have an end point.
A message that doesn't have an end point
is like
a lecture that never ends, that's
interminable, not so good.
So, in order to make a punchy point, we
have to have a beginning.
We've got a great beginning, because we
know that release is triggered by
an action potential, by calcium, in,
influx and an, and an action potential.
But now we need an end point, and we use
three different mechanisms to terminate
the message of a neurotransmitter.
One just happens naturally, which is
diffusion.
These molecules are going to diffuse out,
and this
post-synaptic cell has ears, but those
ears are
only concentrated right here, so if the
molecule
is over here, the cell isn't hearing about
it.
It doesn't matter.
So, diffusion is a very effective way to
terminate to
end, contribute to the termination of a,
of a message.
The second way is through something called
re-uptake.
And re-uptake [COUGH] are, is typically in
the pre-synaptic terminal.
There are channels or transporters.
They are actually not channels.
They are called transporters and these
transporters take this neurotransmitter
back up and you'll be happy to know that
neurons totally believe in recycling.
They are not going to let that, that
neurotransmitter go to waste.
They'll repackage it.
They'll put it right back into a
new vesicle which is actually recycled as
well.
And so then, this, this cycles back.
So, the neurotransmitter, is taken up by
these re-uptake inhibitors.
I am sorry, these are re-uptake,
transporters.
So, re-uptake is a really, really
important way to terminate messages, and
this is really important for drugs like
serotonin and dopamine.
And there are drugs that act on the
serotonin
and dopamine re-uptake transporters that
can be used
both therapeutically, for instance, to
treat depression.
And also, that unfortunately engage,
circuits that lead to, abuse of drugs.
And so, for instance, cocaine, acts on a
dopamine, transporter.
The third way that we, terminate a message
is through degradation.
And, in the case of degradation, what we
have
is enzymes that sit out here in the
synaptic cleft.
That are just chewing up this, this
neurotransmitter.
[SOUND] It's like Pac-Man.
[SOUND] So, they're just going to eat up
this neurotransmitter, and, the,
the molecule, the neurotransmitter where
this
is really, really important is
acetylcholine.
So, in acetylcholine there is a enzyme
that sits in between the ne, the
pre-synaptic and post-synaptic cell that
eats up
that acetylcholine, and eats it up a lot.
So, very little of it actually makes its
way, acro, all the way across the synaptic
cleft.
If you block that enzyme.
And that enzyme is called
acetylcholinesterase, which is abbreviated
like that.
If you block that, you'll have a lot of
acetylcholine.
Remember that acetylcholine is the
neurotransmitter
that is used by motor neurons.
And so, in fact, this, blocking the
acetylcholinesterase
can be used for therapeutics in the case
of people that are not releasing
enough acetylcholine, or don't have
enough, receptors for the acetylcholine,
we
can boost the amount of acetylcholine
in the cleft by inhibiting
acetylcholinesterase.
And that's useful for people with things
like diseases such as myasthenia gravis.
We can also use, or people
also use acetylcholinesterase inhibitors
for nefarious purposes.
And a lot of pesticides drugs such as
Serin are
based on blocking this and the effect of
that is that the
acetylcholine, there is so much
acetylcholine that floods this
post-synaptic cell
which, in the case of a motor neuron, is a
muscle.
So the motor neuron is talking to a
And now the motor neuron is not ever
shutting up.
That means that the muscle is contracted
and it stays contracted.
Well, it's okay to contract but it's not
okay to stay contracted.
So, imagine if your diaphragm stayed
contracted?
No more breathing.
And so, that, that's the problem with
these acetylcholinesterase inhibitors.
Okay.
And then the final segment we're going to
look at receptors.
How do we hear the message?
How does the post-synaptic cell hear the
message?
[MUSIC]